all right welcome back cohort 5 we're in
our first discussion for chapter 7 so
Andrew thank you
for facilitating feel free to take it
from
here um so yeah uh first meeting on
chapter seven so I'll do what I did with
chapter six and maybe just give a I'll
attempt to give a brief rundown of the
chapter outline sort of layout and
what's going on um that said there's a
lot going on in this chapter and I would
say aside from chapter six those who are
interested in getting started on
building actor inference models are
going to want to kind of give a a kind
of special amount of weight to this
particular
chapter um we do we are introduced to
Hidden Markov models and partially
observable Markov decision-making
processes which PP is a shorthand for
that and it's it's just as of right now
that's kind of the not completely
ubiquitous but most widely used models
for a variety of Behavioral experiments
um that said U couple weeks from now
we'll get into chapter eight where we
talk more about continuous models and um
that'll be for looking at instances
where we're looking at very you know uh
fast time scales and great for things
like motor movements um and just with
things that are much quicker but usually
we're dealing with discret variables so
um chapter
7 quick intro
7.1 uh we focus on models of categorical
variables in discrete time with examples
increasing in complexity so we're
introduced to models of perceptual
processing decision making info seeking
learning and finally hierarchical
inference um and the authors try to um
kind of get at different sorts of
emergent properties including measurable
physiology and behavior from these
models
7.2 were introduced to the hidden Markov
model on a perceptual processing
experiment um this is where where the
the model is of our beliefs about how a
musician's audible notes which are the
observations or outcomes in the model
are generated from a written musical
score which are the hidden States the
actually written notes um they're uh
they simulate the Dynamics of basian
belief updating induced by a sequence of
her notes again the
outcomes
um and then from there it gets into
before I move on to the next section
it's just worth noting all of these
experiments in this chapter more or less
to note very specifically what are the
hidden States uh what are the
outcomes what are our matrices that
we're looking at um the a matrix or
likelihood Matrix probability of
observation given State um our B
matrices which is our beliefs about how
one state moves to the
next uh from time step to time step we
have our D Vector which are our prior
beliefs uh about States just starting at
time step one that's it once you move on
from there uh D is no longer it's in the
equation but it's not repeatedly used at
every time step um although it can be
updated depending on how you're running
an experiment such as from trial to
trial
um so we get to see how it evolves over
time time there are five total time
steps it's another thing important to
note a lot of experiments you'll
typically decide how many time steps
occur or will occur over the course of
your experiment so here there are five a
total of five notes that are played
thanks Daniel for going to figure
7.2 um I guess to get a little bit more
in depth here uh upper left of that
figure shows the the models kind of um
posterior beliefs about States and it's
confidence and so like these lines start
to stretch outward at first it's getting
the the right notes for time step one
and time step two Suddenly at time step
three we get an incorrect note or at
least an unexpected note uh there's a
difference between the observations
which are in the lower right corner um a
certain note is played twice in a row
incorrectly versus um what should have
happened or what we expect expected
which is the top right graph unless you
can see that lightly gray square that is
and the model correctly inferred the
right note one that's in black but it
was thrown off by that incor incorrect
note occurring that's the gray there so
the these are all basically outputs of
the the model as the experiment is run
um at the time of this experiment I
believe they were using mat lab and SPM
is their um kind of you know packages
and software used for for deriving this
experiment so there's a lot of
um um nice functions for producing
graphs and outputs of the experiments so
you can actually see what's going on
when we run run them um moving on
to uh section 7.3 now we have what is
arguably a really key sort of model to
dig into this is where decision making
and planning are introduced
into um an experiment and so now our hmm
becomes a
PDP Um this can be seen let's see figure
7.3 um is a great one to it's kind of a
um Exemplar uh image of a of a PDP where
we have many elements as we had before
we have our uh D Vector the initial
States starting all the way to the left
from there we move on we have our states
we have our outcomes s and O we have our
a likelihood matrices which map the two
we have our B matrices showing going
from state to state um but now what
we've done is we've added policies which
are sequences of actions um that the the
agent holds like it could do this series
of actions it could do this series of
actions and so on um those are all kind
of scored so to speak by what's another
quantity that's been introduced here
expected free energy um which differs
from variational free energy that we've
seen before F uh in that g now invol it
takes into account preferences which are
also c not imaged here but you can see
on the the right um they are denoted in
that like list of equations um and those
impact how G is calculated that is you
kind of are trying to score should I do
this to get what I want should I do this
to get what I want should I do this to
realize my expected or preferred
outcomes or should I do this instead
that is impacting how the agent from
there computes its transitions so what
we've done is introduced action into the
model where Action Now impacts the
environment and it's expected to
impact the the hidden states of the
world that are agent is inferring so
it's it's just kind of like the the
prior example but now we've just added
this whole new dimension of action where
there's an actual
bidirectional um relationship between
the agent and
environment um we are also introduced to
a couple of Concepts whenever um the
authors break down expected free energy
so we have like negative epistemic value
and we also have pragmatic value um this
relates to the famous exploration
exploitation uh debate or dilemma um
there's a broad statement in this
textbook that uh active inference
naturally balances out exploration and
exploitation that's its own kind of
conversation to have and some people
debate that depending on how you want to
Define what balance means the key Point
here is that exploration and
exploitation for uh EX epistemic value
and pragmatic value changing your mind
or changing the world
um are included within the same cost
function if you want to look at this
from a machine learning um perspective
for example or more statistical
perspective or calculus what we're doing
is that we're minimizing this quantity
that is expected free energy and you're
minimize you're minimizing it by
engaging in both kinds of behavior both
of them contribute to minimizing the
same quantity and I believe that is what
is meant whenever they state that um
active inference naturally balances
those two uh kinds of actions that an
agent can take we're also introduced to
other things that you know for the sake
of time I won't go too deeply into but
we are introduced to factorization here
so there are different kinds of States
um that that the agent can try to infer
um they're also so different kinds of
outcomes or sensory modalities that the
agent can try to infer for example um
the yes that figure 7.4 uh the A1 Matrix
is just mapping uh
exteroceptive the exteroceptive modality
or set of outcomes which is basically
where the rat is in the Maze but then
the second Matrix uh a a superscript 2
is
denoting uh the rat's beliefs about
uh the stimulus if there's no stimulus
an aversive stimulus or uh an attractive
stimulus and so the word tensor is used
in this chapter and in previous meetings
there's been some debate over if this is
actually a tensor I believe the idea is
that we're ultimately looking at
outcomes locations and contexts right so
it's this kind of outcomes by locations
by context so it does kind of in a way
if you attempt to to put it together
would be more of a tensor object as
opposed to a matrix it's it's a
collection of matrices here um but
hopefully that helps for anyone who's
been
wondering uh what that term how how that
term's being used um similarly we have
multiple B matrices because we also have
um multiple
contexts uh related to
location skipping ahead a little bit
we're are at least skimming the rest of
this section we have our C vectors which
are composed of um preferen preferences
about location
outcomes um which is C1 uh the rat dis
prefers staying in the same spot
whenever it starts out uh so it's set to
a negative one right um You can you
might expect that if you set that to
zero and kept them all zero there's a
chance the rat might just stay there for
the entirety of the experiment
probabilistically um negative one kind
of gets it moving
um C2 meanwhile has to do with the
stimulus zero uh it's neutral towards
not getting a uh not achieving any kind
of stimulus six because it really wants
an attractive stimulus neg -6 it doesn't
want the aversive stimulus right it
wants the cheese it doesn't want you
know a tiny shock or something along
those lines and finally Ma just as far
as the mathematics go those are all
passed through a sof Max function um
that allows you to both include positive
and negative values whenever you're
initially defining the vectors um and
then also it it normalizes everything
such that we're we're looking at more
like probabilistic um probability
distributions so actually after the math
there um for example the attractive
stimulus is actually 400 times more
probable or we might say more desired
than the neutral stimulus um
and then again we have our D Vector
beliefs about um and and again multip
it's factorized there multiple
modalities so uh the the rat believes
that it's starting at the starting
location with full probability that's
how we said it meanwhile for D2 uh that
has to do with where is this where is
the stimulus that it wants uh it doesn't
know so we have a purely uniform D
Vector there uh half and half
so
um that experiment also includes things
like a big part of it is there's a q um
in the lower position of the Maze and so
this is a great experiment to look at as
well because now we get to see both
epistemic and pragmatic value epistemic
it doesn't know where the reward is uh
the Q gives it epistemic value it gives
it information about where the reward is
such as in the image there it's it the
time step one rat starts at beginning
location time step two rat moves to the
Q at the bottom of the maze it uh the Q
tells it that it's at the left position
that's the location of the reward
finally time step three rat smart rat
follows that Q moves to the attractive
stimulus at the left position um which
is pragmatic value realizing its
preference that it does want aches so so
we we we end up with kind of this you
know two-step process where it derives
epistemic value from the que pragmatic
value from actually achieving the the
attractive
stimulus
um so those are some key ideas in active
inference in general and yeah again kind
of an Exemplar model to wrap your head
around um especially for those who are
still kind of trying to understand the
material here because there's a a
significant amount but this is a great
starting point point for really trying
to get into to
modeling um section
7.4 have a model of information seeking
this is a kind of an a cade experiment
um where an agent looks at four
different squares um this does start to
break down things like uh it breaks down
epistemic value further um rather
lengthy explanations of these terms but
but they can be very important and
they're uh very helpful for
understanding the behavior so um those
uh squares there uh all the way to the
left this is where all of the squares
are given uh equal epistemic value right
they're um the agent will look at any of
them with roughly the same frequency uh
in the middle one however um in that
situation the top left square is uh by
the person who set up this experiment
and its distribution um they gave the
top left Square more expected ambiguity
which is one of the the terms that's
derived from epistemic value um beliefs
about that square are less precise
they're more uniform uh in the a matrix
for this Square the likelihoods uh you
can kind of equate this with uh the
street light effect the idea that if
someone is out at night they drop their
keys um they don't know where they are
they will probably look where there's
more light first so they the idea is oh
it's expected that you will actually be
able to minimize your uncertainty or
reduce your uncertainty by looking at
the other three squares here uh whereas
the top left one just imagine it's as if
that square is is is blacked out or or
not well lit or dim or something right
there's it's going to be hard to derive
any kind of epistemic value from it
because it's not things are not very
visible um so that's an attempt at
getting at how to understand expected
ambiguity and finally top right uh or
excuse me the rightmost um image uh here
all of the squares are still visited um
but the B transitions are made to be
less
predictable um and so it's uh the lower
left yeah the lower left square is given
a higher post posterior predictive
entropy so the agent is less sure about
what what will be seen if the cic is
chosen for this square if they keep
looking there it's as if it's as if they
uh are unsure if there will be new
information to get out of that square so
they keep returning to it again and
again um whereas for the other squares
those are more equivalent in the idea
that oh you look at them they don't
really change why look back again right
so it visits all of them but it keeps
checking out the lower left
one um we do have box
7.1 which introduces us to it's been
mentioned before in the textbook but
this is just a quick rundown of trying
to describe uncertainty and precision or
um priors over Precision so that's a
term that basically it it start you it's
like game
control uh from the neural process
theory that we've looked at uh
previously especially in chapter 5 um
this is kind of like at amplifying not
adding to but rather amplifying certain
neural signals um Precision is inverse
variance so something has very high
variance it means it has low Precision
um kind of hard to trust something that
has very high variance or very low
Precision meanwhile um High Precision
means oh that's seems more trustworthy
whenever carrying out your computation
so it's in a in a sense it's like
waiting uh differently all of these
different objects the different matrices
or particular beliefs or otherwise uh
within the
model um section 7.5 learning and
Novelty um this is where we're
introduced to beliefs about
parameters um so this shows us we're
showing this
on page 141 figure
7.10 or 7.10
um it's basically the same model as
before except now we can see all these
additional
nodes uh where all of our different
objects are
parameterized so our likelihood matrices
the a matrices those are all
parameterized by tiny a or small a um
same thing for the B matrices
parameterized by small B um C Small C
and so on
um those mesh really well with looking
at things like Precision because we're
looking at things like waiting um so
these are all parameters that can be
learned as well over the course of a
series of
experiments
um and typically in active inference
models this uh learning occurs at a
slower time scale um which is also kind
of seen in the final example of the tech
of of this particular chapter um that
has to do with hierarchical inference
but basically these parameters can be
learned as well like how you can learn
over time how much to
trust uh certain likelihood mappings
versus others or
trusting uh your beliefs about
transitions versus others or which um
policies to take versus
others things like that um
brief mentions about other things um
I'll leave
them off here but it has to do with
choosing conjugate priors whenever uh
developing um variables that are linked
together concentration
parameters uh the importance of dislay
distributions for categorical variables
where observations and states are kind
of counted over the course of an
experiment um the more you see this the
more you expect it to happen it also
helps us to remember that like a model
like how quickly it will update so you
know you flip a coin five times you see
it's always heads uh you might quickly
come to a conclusion that uh it's an
unfair coin meanwhile if you flipped it
a hundred times with a 5050 of heads or
tails and then you just happen on the
next five tosses to get um all heads
you're much less likely to think oh well
this is an unfair coin because clearly
it was pretty fair the first hundred
times around right so by accumulating
more counts um that informs us about how
much the the model or the agent might
update its beliefs after the next you
know new observation that comes
in we have a mention of structure
learning which is an entire topic on its
own and there's a lot of work still
being
done uh on structure learning but it's
rather interesting uh I'll just briefly
mention this is seen as something like
offline
learning um it there's a metaphor used
for it like that occurs during sleep um
that is the model or agent is not taking
in any new data and yet it's actually
updating its beliefs um but more
specifically what it's doing is that
it's scoring the model it currently has
of the world uh let's say and uh during
this this sleep or resting offline state
it can actually uh compare that model
that it has now with let's say a simpler
model that maybe has removed some of the
certain variables or or or readjusted
and minimize some of its matrices or
otherwise to see um if it can produce uh
an equivalently if not better performing
model um that nonetheless has some of
its complexity reduced and suddenly it's
computationally more efficient right so
so basically in a sleeper resting state
we have basian model reduction um is is
one way that can occur where the model
is kind of pruned and and improved um
even though there's no uh additional
data coming coming in at the
moment and then finally um SEC section
7.6 hierarchical or deep inference um
this again is very similar to um the PDP
that we we saw previously except now we
have an entire additional level added
above um this is figure 7.12 on page 148
and so um I would say briefly that um
the observation nodes uh in the middle
between level one and level two that's a
bit of a
misnomer um there what's going on is
that the state inference occurring at
the lower level is being fed up into
level two uh as if they were
observations at level two um there I I
note this because in a lot of um other
papers that I've personally read uh
usually they would not include those
extra observation nodes in the middle
they would just go straight level one up
to level two um but this is a nice way
of illustrating like it's as if those
are observations for level two so what's
going on what we have at level one
multiple time steps like three time
steps uh vers for every single time Step
at level two so this demonstrates that
there are multiple time scales going on
here level one is happening at a faster
time SC scale there three time steps for
every individual time Step at level two
um the state predictions occurring at
level two are being fed
into uh the uh computations at level one
and so it's like we have these
descending um predictions coming from
this higher level and then meanwhile
level one's State inferences are acting
as
ascending um observations uh if that's
useful and um so this is um I would
maybe I'll drop um an article uh link
into the chat but I think that there's a
rather nice um paper that that I've
spent time reading and I I find personal
interest in it um but it's it's a paper
called deeply felt affect uh which came
out a couple of years ago and it relates
to I would say Fields like computational
psychology or psychiat
um but why I think it's useful for
anyone who wants some further reading
here is that um it one is a recreation
of the tze experiment uh that we saw
earlier uh and on the other hand it adds
a hierarchical layer um that is
theorized in the paper to relate to
emotion and so we have a rat that is um
given this kind of emotional or
affective layer to its model and it
actually dramatically changes its um Its
Behavior whenever navigating the maze uh
it becomes much more confident uh
depending on its emotion in its own
model of how to achieve the reward um
sometimes to the degree that it will
skip the epistemic value from the que
it'll go straight to the reward why
because now it gets an extra time step
that it gets to spend with the reward um
so it's it's again it's just we have the
teamas we have a hierarchical model and
then finally we get to see how like
Behavior changes whenever we add this
hierarchical layer and whenever it comes
to cognitive modeling that's a big
aspect right it'll be to kind of fiddle
around with what variables do you need
uh in your model what are the layers to
be
included um and and how do you kind of
tune or prune things from there um I
feel like I've spoken more than enough
so I will now uh open the floor if
anyone has any thoughts or questions or
just general things you're
considering
um sorry
is
pach uh actually I have a very basic
question uh since we have been talking
on matrices is the D Vector just like a
onedimensional vector that's it yes
nothing else oh wow so I will say in the
so we saw the te uh experiment for
example and in that case we did have two
vectors
uh one for each uh modality so the first
one was yeah the the rat's belief about
where it starts so the location uh
factor or modality and then D2 its
beliefs about where the stimulus is is
it to the left is it to the right here
it's uh you know hardcoded as uniform uh
as a starting point but yes uh they are
each uh 1D vectors um and that's all you
need to kind of kick off or start the
the simulation whenever you're running
it yes so that is mapped to the number
of factors of the B Matrix
right yes to the edge The Edge length of
B okay
yeah because B maps from hidden state to
Hidden state so whatever the number of
hidden States is that b is just that per
slice and then the number of slices of B
is equivalent to how many affordances
there are and then D is just the edge
length that's carried through with s and
then a is O * s because it Maps o and
s pi is also a list with the
probabilities of the actions in the
policy space summing to
one thank you
yeah
I have one question
sorry uh in like actually like when you
normally try to initialize these vectors
say uh say d can you just also hardcode
it like just like one and then just pass
it
right
yeah yeah that's right you would you
would hardcode it um that's one of the
kind of theoretical discussions around
active inference right is it's it's more
about the what and the the why and the
how but not so much about how it starts
um that said what you can also do as far
as learning and inference goes is you
could have um you could set up an
experiment that runs over multiple
trials uh in that case you would still
hardcode D but going from trial to trial
you could have it such that the agent
actually updates uh deep over time so
that trial one it begins with those
hardcoded values trial two it might
update um you know now that it's the
start of trial two what is what are its
prior or initial beliefs about the state
yeah yeah so like in this case let's
just say it was GNA do three rounds of
the
teamas and then initially it has a a
flat uh you know it has a certain it
believes it starts in a certain setting
that that could be that that would be
the D1 location or maybe that one stays
the same the one z00 Z and then the one
it's like it learns by the end that it
it it always starts on the right or
updates it towards the fact that it's
that the reward of the other the stimul
food is on the right side it could learn
that by just counting up okay it was on
the right it was on the right it was on
the right and than that kind of like
putting Pebbles of different color into
the N that's the learning by
counting which is reflected here with a
little D over
the learning by counting on this one so
this one starts out Z 0 it starts out
one one and then you add one every time
you observed it and then that ends up
that's a hyperparameter on the D
distribution so hence the kind of
strategy of the book of showing like the
minimal figure 4.3 type model and then
here's like one Motif which is hyper
priers for learning or attention like
Andrew mentioned here's another Motif
nested models but the hyper priers are
not
shown you can start to combine these but
then you can also imagine how the models
complexity grows a
lot sorry what do you mean by motive
like here The Motif that it's showing is
just nesting it's not including Little D
so it's not like it this is not a
generalization of the previous
one this is just like a generalization
of the of the figure 4.3
one
as this one is but this one's not
nested so like here but the difference
that it's trying to show is just about
the idea of putting this the metallic
lowercase above each of
letters a b c d
e and then these motifs get kind of
combined
okay
um question
yeah slightly slightly tangential so
Andrew in the react FX um project that
you're doing are you building these
types of models I know it's very simple
question um well we've just kicked off
the the project a couple weeks ago so
we're still kind of trying to
decide what kinds of models to build but
anyone who's interested can can
certainly you know hop on and and see
what's going on we do have a a distinct
Coda for that and so right now people
are running project ideas and so they're
like in a table that you can just put in
like oh I would like to try doing
something like this and then maybe put a
couple notes on on what direction you
think it might take and um yeah as
Daniel's pulled up here uh for me I
wanted to see if we could do kind of
reproducibility project where we take
some of this you know few years old code
in mat lab or SPM can we run it through
uh Julia and RX and fur instead um just
basically to see if we can to help with
reprodu reproducibility and from there
we could even potentially start moving
into like modifying those models or
maybe improving
them yeah generally I would it seems
like pdps might be one of the primary
ways that we go so hopefully that
answers your question and is that all I
I see Daniel posted the links in the
chat and I I'll take a look um but is
that all happening at this point
asynchronously through Koda or are there
um Thursday meetings Okay this what you
got up here on the and we're developing
out the GitHub repo and so on so
there'll be but there's there's more
than ample sync and synchronous
opportunities if people want okay and
and it's I mean and there's no chapter
six for RX and fur but these are some of
the um it um I mean we can go more into
this another time but we've like talked
about how we can best contribute and
right documentation so for people right
so it's more I mean it's still sorry
sorry but it's it's still the underlying
strategy yes
we're learning this package for
generative model that's also over the
course of the Year going to increase a
lot in its capacity and
usability okay cool all right I'll pull
up that Cota thanks a
lot and just to note it'll also be
incorporating um you know some research
that's been done since the publication
of the textbook we're looking at so um
you know there'll be a little bit more
uh up to dat so to speak the the
textbook is still a Cornerstone of of
active inference but that said there
than some you know certain kinds of
updates that have been made since then
yeah I would just I would just love to
see this um those modeling applied with
you know actual values if you will it
will help me wrap my mind around it cool
yeah
absolutely um I did notice uh Susan
posted a question in the chat how would
reflection versus indecision be
represented um
I find that to be a rather interesting
question myself and uh while that's not
directly answered by the textbook uh
surely there are papers that have been
published on the these kinds of topics
um but in any case intuitively I would
say just to kind of stay with the
chapter
itself uh
chapter excuse me uh page 145
146 um this is uh an agent navigating a
maze and in this case
um uh the agent is does not have any
specified like particular preferences or
rather that it's like purely uniform
preferences and so the a it's as if the
agent doesn't prefer anything in
particular uh whenever the model is set
up in that way then the agent uh engages
in what could be viewed as an emerging
Behavior called novelty seeking where it
just keeps going to places that it
hasn't been to yet uh you know there
there's no preference for a certain
reward or stimulus to where it knows
that it wants to go to a space that has
a reward right so it doesn't go there it
just goes everywhere um that said it's
still doing it's still following the FP
it's still minimizing expected free
energy or variational free energy and so
uh it will avoid spaces it's already
been to because it's already been there
um nothing new to get no new epistemic
value to be derived from a space you've
already been to and so it will just kind
of like run the full gamut of all the
spaces it's never been to uh this is a
phenomena that's also been referred to
by pner in 1985 is the inhibition of
return so that's that's a pretty
interesting thing to see and it makes a
lot of sense because when we look at our
equations C uh C vector or preferences
are uh heavily informing G and
so there's nothing informative about SE
because it's purely uniform you know uh
nothing nothing's particularly preferred
then it doesn't really help with you
know figuring out what to do other than
just keep keep running around getting
getting all that novelty you can U maybe
it's thrill seeking um it's a joke but
reflection meanwhile not so sure
intuitively might have a relationship
with structure learning um you know an
agent doesn't necessarily have to be
sleeping in order to uh kind of tune or
prune its model um but the idea is that
yeah there's no incoming sensory data so
reflection might relate to that process
you know someone who's sitting there
reflecting uh kind of thinking through
things through even though they've not
pres been presented with anything new um
might be a for struct learning there
might be a paper out there um or or a
dozen uh on these kinds of things worth
worth uh searching for that um but yeah
very interesting question
um yes uh
Anna I see put you're muted
MD
can you hear me okay now yes okay okay
sorry about that uh yeah I was wondering
if you could elaborate on a little bit
on
um the offline updating of of
beliefs um and I'm curious about the
scientific studies that have been done
demonstrating that this in fact happens
that you can you're you know during
sleep or maybe meditation or daydreaming
right can you elaborate a little bit on
how active inference scientists have
looked at this
aspect about active
inference so just be direct in saying
that yeah I'm not personally too sure of
the research that's been done very
specifically on structure learning in
related in relation to
actual sleep um or meditation I mean I'm
seeing just from a a quick all show one
this is not exactly AC but it's it's B
it's right there I'll put it in the
notes this is kind of a g there's many
similar architectures done in machine
learning where there's this
phasic um
approach W with extending and updating
during the day with a fast inference and
then um using different techniques for
sleep and I mean it it probably gets
into the specifics of the machine
learning architecture and then also
there's the whole other angle you said
like
empirically um what what's happening at
the synoptic level and at like the
cognitive level for humans and skill
consolidation and sleeping learning
consolidation naps there's there's
probably a lot of different phenomena
like
that thank you
just drop this here but this looks to be
a manuscript by a couple of researchers
as well who uh make a mention of
particular meditative
Traditions um but they claim there that
as opposed to it being um structure
learning per se they they claim that
meditation is more of a form of like
it's it's a particular It's A peculiar
policy itself um that is you're choosing
to do that um that actually looks to be
a really interesting paper and I
appreciate that there's a more U kind of
culturally accurate as opposed to highly
abstract um kind of theme to it so um
yeah
Susan so yeah this is fascinating um
thank you Andrew
so what uh what keeps coming up is is is
the reference to
you know learning is takes time or um or
you there's no fast learning and so
I'm I'm wondering if maybe the concept
of learning
itself is you know is is um more
specific than I guess what we um what we
generally think about learning so I mean
how would you
categorize learning or or well maybe why
that why it keeps referencing that
learning is
slow slower than
what yes this is a great question I'll
give a first thought um especially as as
more complex cognitive models are built
there's several ways that different time
scales of adaptation happen so the
fastest layer is called inference
and that's kind of like the rubber hits
the road like each um new observation
coming in but also the whole process is
called inference um but also the fastest
layer is called inference then um the
next slowest layer is attention so like
attention modulates um on over multiple
sensory Cycles like just thinking about
the visual case or the the dinner party
like overhearing multiple conversations
like attention module
faster than um slower than the words
coming in but um faster than updating
like deeper factual beliefs and then
then
learning um as distinguished from those
other kinds of parameter
changings is like here being modeled
explicitly with these Hyo priers and
updating the distribution that the kind
of rubber hit the road parameters are
being drawn from that's not the only way
to model
learning so hence chapter six and really
digging in with like what time scale
analysis is being studied because maybe
whether it's learning over seconds like
uh repeating back a phone number or
whether it's like a um semester level
maybe that's the time scale of your
model so then that learning is happening
on the kind of primary time scale of the
model
it's just way too General to say without
specific system of interest but that
being said there are multiple ways that
like to kind of and the hierarchical
models like looked at so multiple
non-exhaustive or exclusive ways to
model the multiscale temporal dynamics
of
change yeah I I would definitely second
uh Daniel's point about yeah it's it
there is no single answer to the to the
question again we have this final
example in this particular chapter
referring to yeah words and sentences
right so those time scales don't seem
dramatically different actually right
like we're looking at a matter of let's
say milliseconds versus seconds um like
predicting what the next few words are
going to be an entire sentence to try
and capture something like what the
sentence is about versus the the faster
time scale of word word word word like
word to word um in the in the sentence
but I I did want to mention a couple
other uh as far as like um trying to map
this to uh Concepts or behaviors in
Neuroscience um another way of thinking
not necessarily thinking about it this
way but one potential analogy could be
something like working memory versus
versus long-term memory uh right like
like here's your quick access like
working memory memory of the Moment by
moment long-term memory occurs over time
you know it gets
Consolidated um slowly over time and it
it can lead to long-term changes in
things like uh your daily habits um what
comes more naturally or quicker to you
so it just describing it a bit more
intuitively that way yeah I like to
sometimes think of it as like yeah
shortterm versus long-term memory then
in addition to that as we saw in chapter
five uh in terms of the neurobiology
um it's commonly been found or or
theorized from from various studies when
working with neuroimaging data that uh
whenever a participant in these studies
is learning something uh what happens is
that that you tend to find when looking
at brain rhythms from let's say EEG um
that uh more Theta and gamma waves are
present simultaneously and so they view
it as what would be called a Theta gamma
coupling we do get a reference to that
in chapter 5 in this textbook um Theta
rhythms are slower uh in a in a
particular kind of Rhythm band or
frequency band uh gamma are faster and
so what happens is these rhythms kind of
um you know it's kind of fun you can
think of it as like music you know you
have some fast drums and a slow piano or
you know some such thing but there's a
kind of sinking between these two uh
differing rhythms and it it is seen as
refle um being a kind of neural
correlate to someone learning something
um so multiple time scales in a PDP
multiple time scales in how our memory
Works multiple time scales in Neuro
Imaging data just a couple more uh kind
of metaphors is Food For
Thought So one one more question that
um it almost I think I'm wrong but it
almost makes me want to wonder um if um
if the learning in this sense isn't
um is it an effect
of
um
[Music]
um actually acting on a
policy but that may or may not be
correct but the other thing that comes
to mind
um would be
would would
surprise occur at either level in other
words if they if they don't learn or if
their policy doesn't um get the expected
payoff then you know there would be a
surprise but also learning would could
actually Encompass a surprise as well
so makes me want to say that there's a
almost a surprise
tolerance yeah like thinking back to the
chapter 2 the basian surprise is the
Delta of
learning and so if if the hyper priors
are
fixed the basing surprise is going to be
zero no matter how surprising in the
first sense the observation is like we
think that the room is this temperature
and we're not open to learning we' have
fixed hyper prior and then even shocking
observations just continue to shock US
versus if you had um like a kind of
adaptive learning rate then there would
be some like a surprising observation
would come in that would catch your
prior wherever it initially was and then
that would also move your prior some
amount over to the new observation so if
that kept happening eventually like you
would converge so that that was no
longer surprising and then how fast you
converge is
attention slash the learning capacity
over different time scales so learning
capacity would would come into the level
of Tolerance I
guess would
coincide thank you and uh forgive me um
to clarify so learning capacity is
represented through those hyper
priors yeah um indirectly yes like like
when Andrew mentioned the coin flip it's
like when um and this is just um you
could see this in any kind of uh basian
statistics overview like if you only had
flipped the coin twice and you got one
in one then you'd have a wide prior
centered around 50% because your maximum
likelihood estimate for the fairness of
the coin is 50/50 but it's very
dispersed it can't be zero can't be 100
because you know that you've seen at
least the other things but but it's
broadly like it's it's a very over
dispersed and then if it was 1 million
and 1 million then the the the the two
millionth and one flip would be very
tight would only move the distribution a
tiny
amount so that's like that learning by
counting and then as you count up more
and then so then then you have this
whole question of okay well then but
then that just slows down our learning
rate but maybe it's a cell
differentiating and it does slow down
its learning rate to a halt or maybe
there's another process that takes a
look at that um learning by counting
variable says when this is 100 we cut it
down to
20 and and that's this whole challenge
with the iterated modeling is figuring
out all these like second order rules
and diagnostic
to be like okay should we cut out 20 or
like 30 and then those are all the like
simulations and sweeps that you do and
then investigate how the agent is
behaving in different
regularities got you thank that's a good
explanation that's a lot of
compute it is so even that's one very
interesting thing which is like even
when like the model as
parameterized might be low compute to
run the open question is how much did it
take to get there not dissimilar to like
a language model where in the forward
running of a trained model it's not Mega
computationally expensive but then
training it can be expensive and
similarly while updating the model might
not be expensive so for a toy model
we're just whatever you make you let it
run and it's all
good but to find like adaptive and
resilient ranges of parameters with many
many
possibilities that can be running these
models many
times cool
well we
return for chapter 7 part two next time
or feel free to
join chapter two it's kind of funny
chapter 2 and chapter 7 they
are very similar and in Chapter 2 we
kind of reference chapter 7 because
that's where the discreet time models
are then chapter 7 took us back to
chapter 2 with the surprise and
everything
so oh thank you Cheryl I'm going to copy
this
in you're welcome thank
you okay farewell bye he bye bye every